Decommission Unix servers

Create change control, get approval and do all the necessary paperwork.

Send ticket to Openview team to stop monitoring the server.

Send ticket to Netbackup team to stop backing up the server.

Send ticket to GIOS Operations Entitlement to remove the server from Entitlement database.

Unmount NFS mounts from clients when necessary and unexport the filesytems.

Return the SAN storage after clearing PVIDs and destroying the VGDA. Send a ticket for cables reclamation and any storage zones etc to delete.

Remove OV client

sudo /usr/local/scripts/removeOV

Send a ticket to OV team to remove it from Openview and NNM.

Remove CDs/Tape media from the server.

Shutdown the Operating system.

Remove the host from pgnmsv01:/prod/images/etc/unix_sys_console

Remove the host from pgnmsv01:/prod/images/nimserver-utilities/Disaster.Recovery.List

Remove the host from penmsv01:/prod/images/nimserver-utilities/Disaster.Recovery.List

Remove the host from PowerVM monitoring / LPAR2RRD.

Remove the LPAR/Blade/Frame as applicable.

Remove the HMC/ILO network/VMWare as applicable.

Unrack where applicable.

Request to remove from hardware maintenance. Email System model number and serial number to Robert.

Remove from UUMA

Remove the mksysb backup files.

Remove from NIM definitions.

Send ticket to reclaim DNS names, IP addresses, network ports and cables to Network team.

Backup the configuration / validation prior to a major OS work on a server

Copy the pre-upgrade directory from NIM server pgnmsv01 to the host(all references to host is to be interpreted as the server we are going to patch.

Login to pgnmsv01

sudo rsync -avv /prod/images/scripts/Pre_Upgrade/ <host>:/tmp/Pre_Upgrade/

Login to the host and execute the saveenv script

sudo /tmp/Pre_Upgrade/aix_upgrade/save_env.sh

This will create a directory in your home directory that contains all the backup files.

For AIX migrations ( not TL upgrades ) Make sure you check the Language Environment in the file “LANGUAGE” in the directory just created by this script. NOTE the FIRST line “LANG=” and the last line for the language reference number YOU WILL NEED THESE at the Initial Migration Configuration Settings.

Make sure that the lppchk outputs are all 0 byte files

ls -l <directory>/pre-lppchk

Login to pgnmsv01 and copy the backed up configurations from the host

sudo rsync -avv HOST:/home/YOURID/HOST-pre_upgradeDATEANDTIMESTAMP/ /preupgrade/reports/HOST-pre_upgradeDATEANDTIMESTAMP/

Login to the host and preserve a copy of rootvg

Disable the alt_disk_copy script

sudo touch /var/adm/do_not_run_alt_disk_until_removed_tenneco

On a SAN booting system,

Find out the alt_disk

lspv | grep rootvg
hdisk0          00021ffb513afe5a                    rootvg          active
hdisk1          00021ffb513aff90                    altinst_rootvg

In this case hdisk1 is the alternate boot disk.

Remove the current alt_disk_rootvg

sudo alt_rootvg_op -X altinst_rootvg

Create a fresh alt_disk_copy

sudo alt_disk_copy -B -d hdiskX

-B option makes sure that it does not execute a bootlist - FYI.

Check altinsta_rootvg has been created

lspv | grep rootvg

Make sure you see the altinst_rootvg in the output

On a mirrored rootvg system do this,

Unmirror the VG

sudo unmirrorvg rootvg hdiskX

Remove the disk from rootvg

sudo reducevg rootvg hdiskX

Clear the VGDA

sudo chpv -c hdiskX

Set the bootlist to boot from the remaining disk

sudo bootlist -m normal hdiskY

Perform an alt_disk_copy to the alt_rootvg

sudo alt_disk_copy -B -d hdiskX

Make sure that NIM server has a latest copy of mksysb

On the server to be patched, find out the NIM server

grep mksysb /var/adm/.information
mksysbhost:pgnmsv01

In this case, it is pgnmsv01

Login to the NIM server we figured out above, make sure a latest copy of mksysb image backup exists

sudo ls -l /mksysb-images/bos.obj.<hostname>.gz

Check the timestamp on the file, it has to be less than 3 days old. If the mksysb is 3 days old or less Proceed to Step 8

On the server to be upgraded create a new mksysb image. When the command has completed proceed to next step

 sudo /usr/local/scripts/mksysb.sh adhoc 

Copy the mksysb image to the repository - This is the backout of last resort.

 sudo cp -p /mksysb-images/bos.obj.<hostname>.gz /preupgrade/mksysb/ 

Configuring sudo

Discuss and make sure what users ask for is legit.

Backup the master file.

sudo cp -p /prod/images/etc/sudoers /prod/images/etc/old/sudoers.$(date +%m%d%y%H%M)

Edit the master file on pgnmsv01

sudo vi /prod/images/etc/sudoers

Make the changes, copy the sudoers to a test system i.e. atlasdr, panmsv02 etc and test if the file is ok. If there is a typo, it will fail on syntax.

Push the file

sudo scp /prod/images/etc/sudoers panmsv02:/etc/sudoers

Test it on panmsv02

ssh panmsv02

Test it

sudo su -

Once tested, copy the file to all the systems. As root,

for host in $(cat /prod/images/etc/allhosts.tenneco)
do
   echo "Copying to ${host} .."
   sudo scp -o Batchmode=yes /prod/images/etc/sudoers ${host}:/etc/sudoers
done

Ignore the errors unless it is the server you want it to go.

As the sudo project did not go initially the way wanted it to go, we had to change the policies a little bit.

No more itocroot requests, we will not reset itocroot's password for any one.

The access will be given to an individual hence there is no need to share the password any more.

The access will not be given to extended period of time

Enabling a user for sudo su - access

No more sudo access here unless there is an exception.

Login to pgnmsv01

Enable xxx user for yyy host

sudo /prod/images/scripts/manage_sudo enable xxx yyy

# yum list installed # yum list packageName # yum remove packageName

Remove unwanted.

chkconfig –list | grep '3:on'

Turnoff ipv6

#See all set user id files: find / -perm +4000 # See all group id files find / -perm +2000 # Or combine both in a single command find / \( -perm -4000 -o -perm -2000 \) -print find / -path -prune -o -type f -perm +6000 –ls

find /dir -xdev -type d \( -perm -0002 -a ! -perm -1000 \) -print

find /dir -xdev \( -nouser -o -nogroup \) -print

Remove

ca::ctrlaltdel:/sbin/shutdown -r -t 4 now

chkconfig –list | awk '/xinetd based services/,/””/' - will show you all processes/services controlled be xinetd.

route | grep link-local

How to disable zeroconf:

  1. edit /etc/sysconfig/network and NOZEROCONF=yes
  2. remove all traces of avahi. 

SSH Config / Lockdown

A few things you must (should) do. There are a pile of other options you may want to consider.

  1. Change the 'PermitRootLogin yes' to 'PermitRootLogin no'
  2. Change the 'ListenAddress' to 'ListenAddress <ip>'. Where <IP> is your management ip address.
  3. Change the 'IgnoreRhosts no' to 'IgnoreRhosts yes'.
  4. Change the 'HostbasedAuthentication yes' to 'HostbasedAuthentication no'.
  5. Change the 'PermitEmptyPasswords' to 'PermitEmptyPasswords no'.
  6. Setup a banner. Add a line 'Banner /etc/ssh/banner' to /etc/ssh/sshd_config and add the following in /etc/ssh/banner (or whatever you like): 

· There are a couple things you may want to add to the /etc/sysctl.conf file.

· # Don't reply to broadcasts. Prevents joining a smurf attack

· net.ipv4.icmp_echo_ignore_broadcasts = 1

·

· # Enable protection for bad icmp error messages

· net.ipv4.icmp_ignore_bogus_error_responses = 1

·

· # Enable syncookies for SYN flood attack protection

· net.ipv4.tcp_syncookies = 1

·

· # Log spoofed, source routed, and redirect packets

· net.ipv4.conf.all.log_martians = 1

· net.ipv4.conf.default.log_martians = 1

·

· # Don't allow source routed packets

· net.ipv4.conf.all.accept_source_route = 0

· net.ipv4.conf.default.accept_source_route = 0

·

· # Turn on reverse path filtering

· net.ipv4.conf.all.rp_filter = 1

· net.ipv4.conf.default.rp_filter = 1

·

· # Don't allow outsiders to alter the routing tables

· net.ipv4.conf.all.accept_redirects = 0

· net.ipv4.conf.default.accept_redirects = 0

· net.ipv4.conf.all.secure_redirects = 0

· net.ipv4.conf.default.secure_redirects = 0

·

· # Don't pass traffic between networks or act as a router

· net.ipv4.ip_forward = 0

· net.ipv4.conf.all.send_redirects = 0

· net.ipv4.conf.default.send_redirects = 0

AIX 7100-05-02 Technology Level Upgrade

Create proper change controls and paper work, get approvals from business, get apps contacts to manage applications etc. As Chris say, the whole nine yards

Verify blackouts are in place for all the servers we plan to work on

Perform the configuration backup

At this point open a console window to the server being upgraded. These reboots to / from the alt disk should be done from the console.

Check that your alt_disk_copy is bootable Note this is extremely important - do not skip this step this is your backout !!!

Find the altinst_rootvg disk

 lspv | grep altinst_rootvg 

and set the boot list so the server boots from it

 sudo bootlist -m normal -o {hdisk from previous command}

Perform a reboot at this time

sudo shutdown -Fr

Verify that the server has booted correcly to the alternate disk.

Rest the bootlist or boot back to the original disk and reboot.

 lspv | grep old_rootvg 

and set the boot list so the server boots from it

sudo bootlist -m normal -o {hdisk from previous command}

and boot back to it

sudo shutdown -Fr 

Cleanup /usr/sap/ filesytem

Check for and commit any uncommitted LPP's left from past upgrades.

List any uncommited LPPS

sudo installp -s

If there are no uncommitted LPP's the output should be

     0503-459 installp:  No filesets were found in the Software
        Vital Product Database in the APPLIED state.

Commit all LPP's (if any) listed in output from installp -s commnd

sudo installp -c all

Check and remove e-Fixes if any on system Below is an example Efixes may vary by release and server depending upon requirements

List e-Fixes if any

sudo /usr/sbin/emgr -P

You should see something similar if the system has e-Fixes

xeerap01:/root> /usr/sbin/emgr -P

PACKAGE                                                  INSTALLER   LABEL
======================================================== =========== ==========
bos.net.tcp.client                                       installp    IV85296s2a
bos.net.tcp.client                                       installp    IV84458s2a
bos.net.tcp.server                                       installp    IV84458s2a
openssl.base                                             installp    102m_ifix

Do Not Remove the IFix for ssl openssl.base installp 102m_ifix This is required for ssl and does not impact the upgrade.

Remove them sudo /usr/sbin/emgr -r -L e-Fix Label

sudo /usr/sbin/emgr -r -L IV85296s2a
sudo /usr/sbin/emgr -r -L IV84458s2a

Make sure /var/log/aso exists

Check if bos.aso is installed

lslpp -l bos.aso

If it exists, you should see something similar

lslpp -l bos.aso
  Fileset                      Level  State      Description
  ----------------------------------------------------------------------------
Path: /usr/lib/objrepos
  bos.aso                   7.1.4.1  COMMITTED  Active System Optimizer

Path: /etc/objrepos
  bos.aso                   7.1.4.1  COMMITTED  Active System Optimizer

If it does, then make sure there is a log directory for it.

ls -ld /var/log/aso

If the directory does not exist, create it

sudo mkdir -p /var/log/aso
sudo chown root:system /var/log/aso

On the NIM server find the correct lppsrc and export the directory to the target server.

To export AIX 7.1 TL 05 SP01

sudo exportfs -i /prod/images/lppsrc/710TL05-02

On the Server to be patched, NFS mount the lppsrc location

sudo mkdir -p /mnt/aixupdates
sudo mount pgnmsv01:/prod/images/lppsrc/710TL05-02 /mnt/aixupdates

For the smitty lovers,

Change to the mount point

cd /mnt/aixupdates

Invoke smitty

sudo smitty update_all

Then select ”.”

PREVIEW only - should be set to no

COMMIT software updates must be set to yes

ACCEPT new license agreements? must be set to yes

Then hit enter :)

For the CLI lovers

Perform a preview upgrade

cd /mnt/aixupdates
sudo install_all_updates -d . -c -p -r -V -Y

If no errors found, perform the upgrade

cd /mnt/aixupdates

If you have a reliable connection i.e. Office, RDP

Start patching

sudo install_all_updates -d . -c -r -V -Y

If you have an un-reliable connection to work i.e. VPN, working remote.

Start patching using nohup

nohup sudo install_all_updates -d . -c -r -V -Y > /tmp/$(uname -n).tlupdate.log 2>&1 &

Watch the progress

tail -f /tmp/$(uname -n).tlupdate.log

More details on the arguments

d  ---> Location
c  ---> Commit the updates
p  ---> Preview
r  ---> Update rpms as well
V  ---> Verbose output
Y  ---> Accept license agreements

Remove the xmdaily entry from /etc/inittab.

sudo rmitab "xmdaily"

Run the following command to remove IBM Electrornic Service Agent Annoying Constant Reminder that fills root mail

sudo /usr/esa/sbin/rmESAReminder

Check for and commit any uncommitted LPP's left from upgrade.

List any uncommitted LPPS

sudo installp -s

If there are no uncommitted LPP's the output should be

     0503-459 installp:  No filesets were found in the Software
        Vital Product Database in the APPLIED state.

Commit all LPP's (if any) listed in output from installp -s commnd

sudo installp -c all

After the upgrade has successfully completed, reboot the server to complete the upgrade

sudo shutdown -Fr

Once the server has successfully rebooted login and check to see that the upgrade completed successfully

Check oslevel

oslevel -s 

Verify against the expected results.

Check lppchk

sudo lppchk -vm3

No output is good.

Verify DS record matches the one that is present in the backup taken prior to the upgrade.

sudo grep DS /etc/mail/sendmail.cf
sudo grep DS /tmp/Pre_Upgrade_report/etc/mail/sendmail.cf

Confirm that the SSH host keys are not overwritten. Login to pgnmsv01, ssh to the server you just upgraded.

 sudo ssh SERVERNAME ls -ld /tmp/

If successful, SSH keys were not over written, we are good. In case of failure due to SSH keys, Restore the SSH keys. First backup the existing one

sudo rsync -avv /etc/ssh /root/etc/ssh.backup/

Restore

sudo rsync -avv /tmp/Pre_Upgrade_report/etc/ssh/ /etc/ssh/